Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf officially is נב Nun
Bet 52. We are a bit behind, we're on נא Nun Aleph
at the bottom, where the גמרא Gemara begins right after the משנה.
Mishnah. And the משנה Mishnah has finally laid out, as I've pointed
out to you many a time, that we get to sort of
what you would have expected to be maybe one of the first
משניות mishnayot way in the middle. So now we finally talk about
the base כתובה, ketubah, about the 100 and the 200 for a
בתולה. betulah. The משנה Mishnah says that anything... sorry, 100 for אלמנה,
almanah, 200 for בתולה. betulah. The משנה Mishnah says that anything less,
or if it was not written in the כתובה, ketubah, does it
matter? It's a תנאי בית דין. t'nai bet din. These are obligations
that exist because the Rabbis imposed them whether they are written in
the כתובה ketubah or not. And then it speaks similarly about the
idea of that's the all of the land is encumbered, the lien
is on all of the property to pay for the כתובה, ketubah,
and similarly if the person tried to limit it and say only
a certain field is encumbered, that he does not have the right.
These are requirements of בית דין bet din regardless of what's written
in the כתובה. ketubah. And then it goes on to other issues
about the obligation to
redeem
the wife if the wife is taken captive. But the first part
is that even if the person either didn't write or explicitly wrote
otherwise in the כתובה ketubah on some of the base obligations, the
100, 200, the שעבודים, shibudim, it does not... it is not effective.
So now let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara at the
beginning of the wide lines, bottom of נא עמוד א. Nun Aleph
Amud Aleph. מני, Mani, who is this going like? רבי מאיר היא,
Rabbi Meir hi, it must be Rabbi Meir. דאמר, D'amar, כל הפוחת
לבתולה ממאתים ולאלמנה ממנה הרי זו בעילת זנות, kol hapoches l'betulah mimatayim
u'lalmanah mimaneh harei zu be'ilat zenut, that anybody who writes for a
כתובה ketubah value less than the standard amount that the Rabbis said,
less than 200 for a בתולה betulah or less than 100 for
אלמנה, almanah, then it is effectively like the woman is without a
כתובה, ketubah, and for the husband and wife to be having sex
without a כתובה ketubah without the protections of marriage, then it's not
like it's even like it's as if it's like fornication. It's like
it's not taking place within the security and the protections within marriage.
So even just anything below the amount that the Rabbis demanded. So
that's an important idea that we'll develop more later. Thank you. Particularly
the idea that the woman, for her to feel protected, especially in
a case where it's unilateral where the husband can divorce her against
her will, if she doesn't have the protection of the כתובה, ketubah,
which makes sure that the husband won't just callously divorce her because
one of the roles of the כתובה ketubah as we've said is
that it prevents the husband from just callously divorcing his wife, he
knows that there's going to be a cost, so he pauses first.
And he knows that if she's divorced she's protected. So if she
doesn't have those protections and she knows he can just easily divorce
her
then to her it feels like it's just casual sex. It doesn't
feel like it's done in the marital context with her with the
sense of the protections that that affords and the commitment that that
has. So that's Rabbi Meir's idea that anything less is בעילת זנות.
be'ilat zenut. Now what does that mean? Does it mean that if
you wrote less in the כתובה ketubah it automatically is voided and
it goes to the standard amount? Or does it mean if you
wrote less in the כתובה ketubah then you're violating and the continued
married life and having sex together is considered a violation, but that
it does not necessarily... but maybe the actual amount of the כתובה
ketubah is what you wrote? Right, do you understand there's two different
issues? One is saying that we censure this. It's unacceptable to have
less than 200 and 100, it's unacceptable, בעילת זנות. be'ilat zenut. It's
another thing to say that if you actually wrote less than that,
that we void what you wrote and we say it's going to
be the standard amount, the 200, 100. The גמרא Gemara assumes that
those are the same. And therefore the גמרא Gemara assumes that the
משנה Mishnah works for Rabbi Meir. Since Rabbi Meir completely opposes a
כתובה ketubah less than 200 and 100, therefore we could say that
if you wrote less than 200 and 100 we void that and
it's the standard amount. So our משנה mishnah is Rabbi Meir. Okay.
די רבי יהודה, De-ei Rabbi Yehuda, because if it's Rabbi Yehuda, האמר
רבי יהודה: ha'amar Rabbi Yehuda: רוצה כותב לבתולה שטר של מאתים וכותבת
התקבלתי ממך מנה, rotze kotev l'betulah shtar shel matayim v'koteves hitkabalti mimcha
maneh,
that if a person can basically write the standard amount, so Rabbi
Yehuda agrees that you need to write the standard... you have to
start with the standard amount, so you write a כתובה ketubah of
200 but then she can write a document and say you already
paid off 100 even if he didn't pay off the 100. Means
you could effectively make the amount 100 once you start with the
document of 200. Or similarly ולאלמנה מנה, u'l'almanah maneh, you could write
the base amount of 100 for the אלמנה almanah וכותבת התקבלתי ממך
חמשים v'koteves hitkabalti mimcha chamishim and she could write a receipt for
50 זוז. zuz.
So you see two things from... so you see from Rabbi Yehuda
that Rabbi Yehuda does not censure the idea of having a כתובה
ketubah less than the standard amount. You might have to start with
the standard amount and then you write a receipt in order to
get it to that
point, but bottom line you have less than the standard amount, he's
okay with that. So the משנה Mishnah assumes that according to Rabbi
Yehuda, now you'll obviously notice that there's a difference here, but the
משנה Mishnah will assume if Rabbi Yehuda says you could start with
200 and write a receipt for 100, then presumably you should also
be able to start with 100. So our משנה mishnah that doesn't
let you start with a lesser amount, the גמרא Gemara assumes that's
only Rabbi Meir. Since in the end of the day Rabbi Yehuda
allows a כתובה ketubah to be less effectively. Then he should be
okay with this משנה Mishnah if the כתובה Kesubah was written for
less. So therefore it assumes that our משנה Mishnah is רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. All right, that's point number one. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa,
let's look now at the end of the משנה. Mishnah. כתב לה
שדה שוה מנה תחת מאתיים זוז, Kasav lah sadei shaveh maneh tachas
masayim zuz, if
the guy wrote that this field worth 100 is the is what
has the the שיעבודים, shibudim, it has the liens on it for
the 200 זוז zuz of the
כתובה Kesubah and he didn't write the standard language of the כתובה,
Kesubah, which is in our כתובה, Kesubah, כל נכסין דאית לי אחראין
לכתובתיך, kol nechasin de'is li acharin l'kesuvaseich, all of my property is
encumbered for the כתובה, Kesubah, so חייב, chayav, nevertheless he is obligated,
the lien applies to all the property, תנאי בית דין tenai beis
din because that is mandated by the בית דין. beis din. Okay,
so אתא לרבי יהודה, ata l'Rabbi Yehuda, one minute, that doesn't work.
We just said the beginning of the משנה Mishnah that says it
can't be less than 200 or 100 is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows it to be effectively less than
200 and 100. This idea that if you wrote a lesser lien,
we ignore that, that sounds like that's going like רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. Why? What רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? דאמר אחריות טעות סופר הוא,
de'amar achrayus ta'us sofer hu, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the
lack of writing liens in a document is considered to be a
mistake of the scribe, which is a funny way of saying that
basically we assume that any loan that you have a שטר shtar
for automatically has liens accompanying it. Whether it's written in the document
that there will be liens on the property or not, the fact
that you have a written loan automatically includes the liens. So the
way we say that is if the liens were not written in
the document itself, well, that was just a טעות סופר, ta'us sofer,
it doesn't mean anything. All right, so therefore the גמרא Gemara is
saying if you wrote, now here clearly you can't be talking about
a mistake of the scribe because the scribe explicitly wrote the only
lien for this כתובה Kesubah is on this one field of 100.
So nobody's making any mistakes, nobody forgot to write something. But nevertheless
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda point is once you have a loan in
a document, it automatically the liens automatically result from that document. So
therefore this משנה Mishnah that says that even if you wrote the
liens only on one field, they apply on everything, that follows רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says a שטר shtar comes automatically with liens,
whether they're written or not, or even if something specifically otherwise is
written in the שטר. shtar. That says the גמרא Gemara goes like
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, דאי רבי מאיר, de-ei Rabbi Meir, because if
it was רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, הא אמר אחריות לאו טעות סופר,
ha amar achrayus lav ta'us sofer, he said if you didn't write
the liens in the document, it's not a mistake and it would
be a loan without liens, דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה,
Mishnah, מצא שטרי חוב, matza shtarei chov, if somebody finds
a loan document
on
the street, okay, it says that ראובן Reuven borrowed $100 from שמעון
Shimon and now you go ahead and first of all so you
don't know who dropped this document, did ראובן Reuven borrow it after
he had paid שמעון Shimon back and it was already a paid
up debt, or did שמעון Shimon drop it and ראובן Reuven still
owed him the money? So obviously you would not go ahead and
give it back to שמעון Shimon because maybe the debt had been
paid. But you go over to ראובן Reuven and you say ראובן,
Reuven, what's the story with this document? I found it. He says,
oh, that's שמעון's, Shimon I haven't paid up the debt yet. So
maybe then you would
assume שמעון's Shimon document, you go ahead and you return it to
שמעון. Shimon. Nevertheless, the משנה Mishnah teaches אם יש בהם אחריות נכסים,
im yesh bahem achrayus nechasim, if there are liens that are included
in this document, לא יחזיר, lo yachazir, you can't give it to
שמעון, Shimon, שבית דין נפרעין מהן, shebeis din nifra'in meihen, because then
בית דין beis din would exact the liens. What does that mean?
It means we're afraid of the following: we're afraid that ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon have decided to use this opportunity as a little
bit of a scheme and therefore what they're saying is like the
following, actually ראובן Reuven has paid up the loan, okay, so he
doesn't owe שמעון Shimon anything. Then but what's going to happen now,
you'll return this document to שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon will come to
ראובן Reuven to pay up the loan again, they have now a
scheme going between them and ראובן Reuven would say oh, I'm sorry,
I don't have any money, so שמעון Shimon would now go and
seize the property that has the liens on it from the people
that bought it off of ראובן Reuven and then they'll split it
between them. Okay, so we're afraid of that and therefore you don't
return the document. Now of course if we were genuinely afraid of
that all the time, then we would say every time ראובן Reuven
pays up a loan, you have to tear up the document, you
can't give it back to ראובן Reuven because maybe they'll just reuse
it, right? So as a general rule we're not afraid. This is
an interesting idea that comes up in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia that
if we find the document lying in the street, that makes us
feel like that makes us suspicious because we basically feel that שמעון
Shimon would never have lost have been so careless with the document,
like this is $100, he wouldn't have been so careless. So if
it's lying in the street it probably fell from ראובן Reuven because
it probably was already paid and therefore ראובן Reuven was more careless.
And that makes us suspicious and therefore we won't give it back
even if ראובן Reuven said that it's שמעון's. Shimon Okay, generally we're
not concerned about this, but you find a lost document, it doesn't
have as much weight because it's lying in the middle of the
street and therefore you can't just give it back to שמעון. Shimon.
Yeah, you would assume even if you gave it to ראובן Reuven
you would write paid on it, so maybe that's also that's true.
Look, from a הלכה halachic perspective or from a למדנות lamdus perspective,
the way of saying this is is that a שטר shtar is
not considered... to be made to testify unless it's being held by
the person who, you know, is the bearer of the document. And
if שמעון Shimon is holding the document it's testifying that ראובן Reuven
owes him the money. If you find it on the street it's
not testifying to anything. So to take a piece of paper and
give it to שמעון Shimon and turn it into testimony is something
that requires a good amount of proof before you're prepared to do
that. Okay. So אם יש בה אחריות נכסים, im yesh ba achrayut
nechasim, if there are liens, לא יחזיר, lo yachazir, don't give it
back, כי בית דין נפרעים מהם. kibeit din nifraim mehem. אם אין
בה אחריות נכסים, im ein ba achrayut nechasim, if there are no
liens written in the document, יחזיר, yachazir, then give it back to
שמעון, Shimon, שאין בית דין נפרעים מהם, she'ein beit din nifraim mehem,
because then there would be no way that the, any, you know,
any third party can be implicated that you can seize the property
that was sold to a third party. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi
Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. Meaning, if there are
no liens written in the document, then it doesn't have liens. Then
you can't then, you know, it doesn't, we don't say that anything
that's a written document automatically has liens. If there are no liens
written in it, then there are no liens. וחכמים אומרים, ve'chachamim omrim,
but the sages say, אחד זה ואחד זה לא יחזיר, echad zeh
ve'echad zeh lo yachazir, either way don't return it, שבית דין נפרעים
מהם, she'beit din nifraim mehem, because the בית דין beit din will
always go ahead and exact the, and you know, and exercise liens
on a written שטר. shtar. So this is the idea that anytime
you have a loan written in a document it automatically entails the
liens that come with it, the שיעבודים shibudim come automatically with it.
And the way the גמרא Gemara phrases that is אחריות טעות סופר.
achrayut ta'ut sofer. We assume it's a mistake of the scribe. But
we don't really mean a mistake of the scribe, because we might
know the scribe like in this case explicitly said, you know, liens
are only on this field etc. and we're still going to say
that there are, you know,
that the liens are on everything. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that
therefore what do we have? רישא reisha רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the
beginning of the משנה Mishnah that says the כתובה ketubah can't be
less than two hundred or a hundred is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
that says anything less is בעילת זנות. be'ilat zenut. וסיפא ve'seifa רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and the end of it that says that if
you had tried to make the שיעבודים shibudim less than they normally
are, that there's still the full שיעבודים. shibudim. That's like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, that says that any document automatically has שיעבודים. shibudim. So
the גמרא Gemara says how do you make sense of it? וכי
תימא, ve'chi teima,
so there are going to be some obvious answers which the גמרא
Gemara will say. וכי תימא כולה רבי מאיר היא, ve'chi teima kulla
Rabbi Meir hi, maybe it's all רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ושני ליה
לרבי מאיר בין כתובה לשטרי. ve'shani lei le'Rabbi Meir bein ketubah lish'tarey.
Maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes a distinction. He says by a
normal document I'll assume there are no liens if it's not written
in. By a כתובה, ketubah, maybe כתובה ketubah is special. By כתובה
ketubah we say that's what the משנה Mishnah means when it says
תנאי בית דין. tenai beit din. So the כתובה ketubah I'll assume
there always are liens. Okay, a normal document not but a כתובה
ketubah yes. ומי שני ליה? umi shani lei? Does he really make
this distinction? והתניא, ve'hatanya, do we תנא tana a ברייתא, braita, חמישה
גובים מן המשוחררים. chamishah govin min hamachrorin.
Five things you can only collect from the unencumbered property. Right, שחרור
shichrur like בני חורין, benei chorin, it's about to be פסח. Pesach.
משוחררים machrorin means the free property as opposed to the משועבדים. meshubadim.
שיעבוד, shibud, עבודה, avodah, right,
you didn't know there was going to be a
פסח Pesach theme here. Okay. So
משוחררים machrorin is your property that's בני חורין. benei chorin. They're not
encumbered, they're free, meaning they're in your control, you haven't sold them
to a third party. So there are five things that do not
have liens, that you can only collect from the property that is
being held by the person who owes you the money, not by
property that actually he has sold to somebody else.
ואלו הן, ve'eilu hen, these are they. פירות ושבח פירות. peirot ve'shevach
peirot. Fruit and the benefit of fruit, which means the following. It's
a case that
somebody
steals a field and sells it. ראובן Reuven steals a field and
sells it to שמעון. Shimon. Okay. Then comes along לוי Levi the
owner of the field and manages to prove it's his and takes
it back from שמעון. Shimon. All right. Now שמעון Shimon goes back
to ראובן, Reuven, however, whatever the court did to ראובן, Reuven, שמעון
Shimon still wants his money back from ראובן. Reuven. שמעון Shimon goes
back to ראובן Reuven to get his money back for paying for
the field. Okay. ראובן Reuven doesn't have any money. So שמעון Shimon
collects the money that ראובן Reuven owed him, right, you get this,
שמעון Shimon paid ראובן Reuven for the field that wound up to
be stolen, anyway שמעון Shimon now goes ahead and gets his money
back from people that ראובן Reuven sold ראובן's Reuven fields to. Is
this confused or you got this? Should I draw this?
Okay. We'll call them גנב. gannav. Okay, we'll call them owner,
גנב, gannav, and buyer. Okay. So this one field was owned by
this guy, stolen by him, sold to him. Okay. Then the owner
comes and he realizes it's his field and he gets his field
back. All right. The buyer now says give me my money. Okay,
he wants to be paid back. Pay me back for the field
that you stole that I bought from you. Okay. The גנב gannav
doesn't have any money to pay him back, okay, but the גנב
gannav has sold his fields, the גנב gannav's fields to these other
people. This will be
ראובן, Reuven, the
one that he really did own.
So he wants his money back so he can't get it from
the גנב gannav but he's... get to get it from the people
that the גנב ganaf? *ganev* sold the field for because when the
גנב ganaf *ganev* sold the field here, that put liens on these
on this property that he had owned at that time that if
that if he ever had to reimburse the guy, the guy would
be able to get them his money back from the from the
property that the גנב ganaf *ganev* had. Okay, so he's going to
now go to the fields that were in the גנב'ס *ganev's* control
when he bought it and therefore he had liens and now they're
under ראובן'ס *Reuven's* control and he's going to go get his money
back. Okay, the only thing is the following: While the field was
in the buyer's control, he was going ahead and he planted it
and he and he you know and and he plowed it and
there's now grain growing and all the whole thing and then when
the owner took it back, he took it back with a nice
improved field, a field that's been plowed and fertilized and with all
this grain. So the buyer has invested that money in that field.
He's entitled to that money back because the whole thing was the
גנב'ס *ganev's* fault. He's entitled to get reimbursed for that investment from
the גנב ganaf *ganev*. Okay, he cannot go ahead he can only
get it from property that is in the גנב'ס *ganev's* direct control.
He cannot get it from ראובן *Reuven* because since that amount is
unfixed, right, if it could be 20 years he's been investing money
in the field or whatever it is, since that's a non-fixed amount,
it's not fair to ראובן *Reuven*. When ראובן *Reuven* bought it from
this guy, he knows there's somebody out there who has a lien
on this field that I might that might seize it, but that
was a fixed amount, right? It would not be fair for ראובן
*Reuven* to buy this and have an indefinite amount that might be
that might be indebted. So that's the basic rule here. You can't
have a lien according to this משנה mishna *Mishna* on on amounts
that are that are like unspecified, indefinite, you know, that might be
that might be ongoing debts. Did you have a question, Dov?
So
the lien is only on the original amount that he paid for
the field? Right, exactly. If the real estate itself subsequently becomes more
valuable...
Right, that he can't collect for because that wasn't his outlay. But
the money he invested in it was his outlay.
Are there limitations on how long that buyer can get the field,
the גנב'ס *ganev's* field, back? Yeah, in other words, the property is
there, any time limits on this?
No, not if it's for the base amount, but for the but
we do limit the you know that it can't be an ongoing
like amount, an increasing amount, right. But no, but there's no time
limit. Okay, so פירות ושבח פירות והמקבל עליו לזון את בן אשתו
ואת בת אשתו *peiros veshavach peiros vehamekabel alav lizon es ben ishto
uvas ishto*. Somebody who obligates himself let's say as a כתובה ketubah
*kesuva* obligation that he will whatever he obligates himself to pay his
stepchildren, his stepson or his stepdaughter, because again מזונות *mezonos* is an
indefinite ongoing obligation. So if he then goes ahead and dies and
the field or whatever or he sold his field let's say he
didn't die, you cannot go ahead and get pay those things off
from fields that are sold because that is a non-fixed amount, that's
an ongoing amount. You might by the way remember the דף daf
*daf* we just did yesterday about the daughters being supported from the
קרקע *karka* that if that land of the estate switches hands, it's
not so clear that the daughters can continue to be supported from
it because again it's an ongoing indefinite amount. Okay, so this can
only be collected from property that is in the person's direct control.
And finally, this is וכתובת אשה שאין בה אחריות achrayus *v'kesuvas isha
she'ein bo achrayus*, I'm sorry, וגט חוב שאין בו אחריות achrayus *v'get
chov she'ein bo achrayus*, excuse me, a normal loan document without without
liens written in it and a כתובת אשה שאין בה אחריות achrayus,
*kesuvas isha she'ein bo achrayus*, a כתובה ketubah, *kesuva* without liens written
in it. So you see explicitly that if there are not liens
written in it, you don't assume liens. מאן תנא לה דאמר אחריות
לאו טעות taut. סופר *Man tana leh d'amar achrayus lav taus sofer*?
Who is he? Who is the one that says that lack of
writing liens is not considered a mistake? We assume that it means
what it says. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*. It's רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir*. And that's and that's why this ברייתא braita.
*braisa* that we just quoted is רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir*
and that's why it says that in a normal document without liens
there are no liens. דתני *D'asni*, and it says that the same
is true by a כתובה ketubah, *kesuva*, כתובת אשה *kesuvas isha*. So
now we have here's so it's clear that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* says that if you don't write liens in a כתובה
ketubah *kesuva* there are no liens. By the way it's pretty interesting,
you would have thought that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* who
is so מקפיד *makpid* that you don't go below the 200 and
100 would also insist on the full normal demands of בית דין
*beis din* of there being liens on the כתובה ketubah *kesuva*. But
maybe again, maybe there he's having to he feels he needs to
protect the purchasers, you know, not just the husband and wife. There
are other people that are involved there. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir,
*Rabbi Meir* says while it can't be less than 200 and 100,
it can exist without liens. And רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*
seems to say the flip: it can be less than 200 and
100, but the liens are full. So who is our משנה mishna
*Mishna* going like? Our משנה mishna *Mishna* saying it has to be
the full 200, 100 and there have to be the full liens.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי בעית אימא רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir. ואי בעית אימא V'ee bayis eima רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *ei
ba'is eima Rabbi Meir v'ei ba'is eima Rabbi Yehuda*. You can make
it work either way. אי בעית אימא רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. התם
כתב לה התקבלתי הכא לא כתב לה Lo kasav lah. התקבלתי *Ei
ba'is eima Rabbi Yehuda, hasam kasav leh hiskabalti, hacha lo kasav leh
hiskabalti*. This was the most obvious answer. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* made a very funny statement. He said you can write a
כתובה ketubah. *kesuva* of 200 and get a receipt of 100. Why
didn't he just say the easier thing? You could write a כתובה
ketubah, *kesuva* of 100. So it's clear that according to רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* you have to start with the base כתובה
ketubah *kesuva* that the Rabbis instituted. You have
to
write
the base כתובה ketubah *kesuva*. so the base כתובה ketuvah has to
be written with that 200. Okay? So one way of explaining the
משנה mishna is, the משנה mishna says you can't have a כתובה
ketuvah less than 200 and 100, who's that going like? Maybe it's
רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda, Although רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says that you
can, you can write a receipt and make it effectively less, you
can't start it off as less than 200 and 100. ואי בעית
אימא if you want you could say רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir מאי
חייבת דקתני מן המשועבדים Mai chayves d'ka'tani min ham'shu'abadim or could even
be רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but when the משנה mishna says that
if you wrote that, you know, you only have a lien on
one field, that you still have a full lien on the כתובה,
ketuvah it doesn't mean that you have a full lien on all
the real estate, it means you only have a lien on the
unencumbered property. I have a feeling that I am losing everybody right
now.
Okay, can I one, can I ask you a question? Yes. Who,
who stands to be paid back for the שבח פירות shvach peiros
of that originally stolen field?
The purchaser, the buyer.
But if the field was stolen, he, in other words, how is
it that it was under his control if it was stolen from,
he spent all those years trying to prove title that it was
really his field and not the גנב?
ganaf Maybe the גנב ganaf had forged a document and then it
was eventually proved and it looked like it was the גנב's ganaf.
and then eventually was proven in court that it never was the
גנב's.
ganaf,
But in the, but in the meantime, all those years the original
buyer had been investing in it?
Exactly, exactly. And he had built a house and he had done
whatever and he had spent $100,000 in improvement.
And then the גנב ganaf comes along and says this is really
my field.
No, the court, the owner comes along and says, the court comes
along and says you bought it from a גנב and the owner
is taking it back and now he wants his reimbursement from the
גנב.
To have in good faith from the גנב, he, you know, he
thought he was the
owner.
Ah, got it, right, right, right. The whole thing was a scam
from לכתחילה. lechatchila. Okay, like the
original
owner
knew,
like if the גנב came along and, ah, okay.
Okay,
so I have a feeling I'm losing people, so here, let me
do this again. Okay, so here you have the,
okay. So, so, okay, one minute.
These are the two
debates, these are the two debates of רבי מאיר, רבי יהודה. Rebbi
Yehuda. Okay, by כתובה, ketubah רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you can
have a כתובה ketubah less than 200 and less than 100, although
the case he gives is that you wrote a receipt, so you
effectively made it less, but at the end of the day, it's
less, whereas רבי מאיר says כתובה ketubah always has to be the
full amount. In general by other documents, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says
that you always assume אחריות if it's written, whereas רבי מאיר says
you only assume אחריות is only present if it's explicitly written in,
and we see he says that even by a כתובה. ketubah Okay,
our problem is that our משנה mishna said that when it comes
to a כתובה, ketubah what did our משנה mishna say? Our משנה
mishna said that כתובה ketubah is always 200 or 100 depending on
אלמנה בתולה almanah besulah and always אחריות,
right? Always, so who is it going like, right? It can't be
going like either,
they don't like the fact that it's always.
So the easiest answer is that it's רבי יהודה, that רבי יהודה
says, yes, effectively it can be less than 200 and 100, but
you gotta start it at the base amount. If you want to
write a receipt afterwards, גזונטערהייט, gezunterheit, you're allowed to, you're allowed to
effectively make it less, but the base amount has to start with
what amount that the rabbis said. So that's the easiest answer that
משנה mishna. is רבי יהודה. The other answer is our משנה mishna
is רבי מאיר, and when the משנה mishna says that if you
wrote that you only have rights, liens on a particular field, you're
still חייב, chayav, it didn't mean that you have liens on the
whole property. It actually means you only have liens on that field.
But what it means is you're still חייב chayav the full amount
from the property that you have that's under your control, but property
that you sold, actually you would not have the, you would not
have those liens and that would be if it were following רבי
מאיר. But that's not the simple sense of the משנה. mishna The
simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is, is that you cannot limit
the liens, the liens are going to be full because that's what
the rabbis demand and therefore it makes sense that our משנה Mishnah
is רבי, is רבי יהודה and that רבי יהודה is saying you
have to start with this base amount even if afterwards you could
effectively make it less.
If this field is not worth 200 זוז zuz and he owes
200 זוז zuz for his divorce price, then he is still responsible
for the other 100.
The question is, is he responsible and then are there liens on
the other property for the other 100 or is he just personally
responsible? So רבי מאיר would say that he's just personally responsible whereas
רבי יהודה would say, and that's the simple sense of the משנה
is that there are liens on the, on the rest of the
property for the other 100. Okay, so now we move on. So
that was about the base amount of the כתובה kesuvah and about
that these obligations exist even without the document. All right, now we
move on. לא כתב לה. Oh my god, we are falling more
and more behind. Okay, אמר רב ושמואל. Amar Rav u'Shmuel. So now
we deal with the issue about, now we get to a, the
issue about the
מצוה mitzvah to redeem The מצוה, mitzvah, the כתובה kesuvah obligation for
a man to redeem his wife, but also the implicit difference in
the משנה that if she's married to a ישראל, Yisrael, then he'll
redeem her and we are going to assume that if she was
taken captive,
she was or might have been raped. If she's married to a
ישראל, Yisrael, he'll redeem her and therefore he will continue to be
married to her. If she's married to a כהן, Kohen, he'll redeem
her but then he'll have to divorce her because even for a
wife of a כהן, Kohen, even if she's raped, she's not allowed
to continue to live with her husband. So let's take a look
now what the גמרא Gemara said about that. Before it gets to
the כתובה kesuvah obligations, it's going to deal with this difference about
the consequences of rape between a wife of a ישראל Yisrael and
a wife of a כהן. Kohen. So let's take a look. אמר
אביו דשמואל, Amar Avud Shmuel, the father of שמואל Shmuel said: אשת
ישראל שנאנסה, Eshet Yisrael Shene'ensa, the wife of a non-כהן Kohen who
was raped, אסורה לבעלה, Asura LeBa'alah, she's forbidden to her husband. חיישינן,
Chayshinan, why? שמא תחלתה באונס וסופה ברצון. Shema Techilatah Be'ones VeSofah BeRatzon.
This is a very, very difficult גמרא Gemara again. You can't imagine
that this would have been that this could ever be written from
a female perspective. But the גמרא Gemara. is saying that we're afraid
that even though she's being raped, somewhere in the middle of being
raped, she actually decides that she wants to have sex with this
guy. Very difficult idea in the גמרא. Gemara Now what the גמרא
Gemara. will discuss later on is that a woman might who is
being held captive and under threat for life and we've seen this
before might agree willingly to have sex because she's doing that in
terms in big picture in terms of trying to protect her life,
right? So the act itself might be willing but ultimately it's because
she's afraid, you know, she's doing what she has to do to
stay alive. As opposed to this, this does not sound like that
at all. This sounds like he actually has already begun raping her
and having intercourse with her and in the middle she's deciding that
she actually wants it. Okay, very difficult גמרא. Gemara Yes, David.
What about how she
was captured and
she
became interested to stay with that person? So I don't know if
this is, oh, you're saying maybe it's not during the same act?
Maybe it's over time, the psychology of
identifying with your captors, you know?
It's interesting. So you're sort of same idea. Okay, that's an interesting
point. But what you mean is it's not during the same act,
similar to what I was saying before, but not in the same
way, meaning we're talking over a period of time that eventually it
becomes ברצון. BeRatzon. Now the ברצון BeRatzon of, it's an interesting point,
because the ברצון BeRatzon of I'm doing what I have to do
to stay alive even though I don't want to do it is
basically considered אונס. Ones. Actually there's a whole discussion of רש"י תוספות
Rashi Tosafot before, but if somebody's afraid for their life and they're
basically willingly having sex with their captors or doing whatever they're doing
but ultimately it's because they feel they have to do this to
stay alive, that very well might be considered אונס Ones ultimately. But
your example is an interesting one. Your example is that eventually you
actually sort of your whole mindset shifts about this and you become
identified with your captors. Interesting. I think we'll see a later גמרא
Gemara that talks about like even in mid-act, you know, and that's
I think the normal assumption we're talking about mid-act. But the way
you're framing it at least makes it possible to imagine what the
גמרא Gemara is talking about. Yes, Charlie. All right, so let's take
a look. Okay, so he says therefore even if it's a case
of being captive, she's forbidden to the wife of a ישראל. Yisrael.
איתיביה
רב לאביו דשמואל, Aisivei Rav LeAvud Shmuel, so רב Rav asked the
father of שמואל: Shmuel: אם תשתבאי, Im Tishtavai, the language of the
כתובה kesuvah is, if you're taken captive, אפרקינך, Afarkinnach, I will redeem
you, ואותבינך לי לאינתו, VeOsevinnach Li Le'intu, and I'll take you back
as my wife. So you see that a woman who returns to
the wife of a ישראל Yisrael after being held captive is allowed
to go back to her husband. אישתיק, Ishtik, he was silent. He
didn't have an answer. So
קרי רב עליה דאביו דשמואל, Karei Rav Aleih DeAvud Shmuel, so רב
Rav then said referring to the father of שמואל, Shmuel, רב Rav
was the one who asked the question, שרים עצרו במלים, Sarim Atzru
VeMilim, that the, you know, great people were held back with their
words, וכף ישימו לפיהם, VeKaf Yasimu LeFihem, and they'll put their hands
to their mouths. So meaning like he was silent but he didn't
have to be silent. מאי הוה ליה למימר? Mai Hava Leh LeMeimar?
He could have had a response. The response could have been בשבויה
הקילו. BiShvuya Hekilu. Our case is a case where the woman is
taken captive. If she's taken captive, we don't know that she was
raped, right? What the father of שמואל Shmuel said is a woman
who was raped. We know she was raped. Okay, if we know
she was raped, then we're afraid that maybe she did in the
end she wanted to do it willingly. Whereas if she's taken captive,
maybe she was never raped. So since it's possible she was never
raped, we allow her to go back to her husband. But if
we know she was raped, we're afraid that she in the end
did it willingly. And that, by the way, David, is why I
think although I would like your explanation to be correct,
the statement of the father of שמואל Shmuel is not specifically a
statement of being taken captive, it's just a statement about a woman
who is raped. Some guy jumps on a woman in the... middle
of the street and rapes her, and she says, oh, she can't
go back to her husband, maybe she did it ברצון beratzon in
the end, right? So it's not a case. The גמרא Gemara actually
says in the case of captivity we're more lenient because maybe she
was never raped. She was talking about a straight case of rape.
The context was really where the husband wrote in the משנה that
he
was afraid of being captured... right, and that's what the גמרא Gemara
says, that that doesn't... that's not... yes, but the גמרא Gemara says
that that שמואל Shmuel would agree she can go back because maybe
she wasn't raped. When שמואל Shmuel said she's forbidden to her husband,
it wasn't a case of being taken captive. It was just a
case of us directly witnessing her being raped, you know. So that's
why, you know, I think that that the גמרא Gemara is... while
I appreciate your explanation, the whole point of גמרא Gemara here is
that שמואל Shmuel was talking about a straight case of rape, which
makes it on the one hand more of a problem because we
know that she had sex with this guy. On the other hand,
you and I and I think would all think that everyone would
all think that how can you imagine that she was willing in
the middle of an act of rape, right? So now and you'll
see in a minute that the גמרא Gemara assumes that שמואל's Shmuel
position is the father of שמואל's Shmuel position is by all things,
not just by, you know, because let's take a look at the
next line. ולאבוה דשמואל, ul-Avua de-Shmuel,
according to the father of שמואל, Shmuel, אונס דשרי רחמנא היכי משכחת
לה? ones desharei Rachmana heichi meshkachat lah?
When the Torah says by the סוטה, Sotah, a woman who's suspected
of committing adultery, it says, והיא לא נתפשה, ve-hee lo nitpasa, that
she wasn't raped, right? So meaning the Torah implies that if a
woman was raped she's allowed to go back to her husband. So
how does שמואל... Shmuel... the father of שמואל Shmuel make sense of
this? The father of שמואל Shmuel says that even if a woman's
raped she's not allowed to go back to her husband, but it's
implicit in the Torah that she is.
So אונס דשרי
רחמנא היכי משכחת לה?
ones desharei Rachmana
heichi meshkachat lah? So כגון דקאמרי עדים, kegon de-kamrei edim, and here
you see explicitly David, against what you were suggesting, I keep on
going back now because I would have liked to have said what
you said, but כגון דקאמרי עדים, kegon de-kamrei edim, the only case
a woman can go back to her husband after being raped is
that the witnesses say שצווחה מתחילה ועד סוף. she-tzvacha mitechilah ve-ad sof.
She was yelling and screaming from the very beginning of the act
to the end. But if somewhere in the middle she stopped screaming
and protesting, then we're assuming that she in the end is a
willing participant. Again, it's like just horrific to imagine this. Okay?
Instead of helping her, they're watching as witnesses.
Well, okay, that's also true, but you know, that... who knows what
the circumstances are. I wouldn't focus on the witnesses at this stage.
ופליגא דרבא, u-pliga de-Rava, this argues on רבא. Rava. דאמר רבא, de-amar
Rava, now because רבא Rava says כל שתחלתה באונס וסופה ברצון, kol
she-tchilatah be-ones ve-sofah be-ratzon, if it began as force even if in
the end it was willing, so again he's not disagreeing with his
understanding of the facts that it's possible that it's willing in the
end, אפילו היא אומרת הניחו לו, afilu hee omeret hanichu lo, even
were she to say, you know what? Don't do anything, don't stop
him. שאילמלא נזקק לה היא שוכרתו, she-ilmaleh nizkak lah hee socharto, that
even had he not forced himself upon me, I would have even
paid him to have sex with me. Okay, so she's a... so
she actually explicitly says this, alright? Even in such a case, מותרת,
muteret, she's permissible. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? יצר אלבשה. yetzer albasha. Her
יצר yetzer got the better of her. Okay, so since she was
forced at the beginning of the process and that was against her
will, even if now it somehow, you know, elicits sexual desire, again
very hard to imagine any of this, and even if it elicits
desire to the point that she says I want to have sex
with him even from beforehand, all of that we think is resulting
from the fact that it all began from a rape and from
an אונס ones and therefore no expression of רצון ratzon should be
considered as רצון. ratzon. Okay? So this is a very important halachic
principle of תחלתה באונס וסופה ברצון... tchilatah be-ones ve-sofah be-ratzon... well actually
no, that's a different principle, but it's actually related. Okay, this is
תחלתה באונס וסופה ברצון, tchilatah be-ones ve-sofah be-ratzon, it's all defined by
the original אונס. ones. There's a different principle, for example, by negligence
issues of תחלתה בפשיעה וסופה באונס, tchilatah bifshia ve-sofah be-ones, which is
let's say I begin... I'm negligent with your object but then some
accident occurs to it. Maybe it doesn't matter, maybe because of the
initial negligence everything that happens afterwards is defined as a result of
the negligence. So this is... that's by sort of torts, right? This
is by this issue, which is any sense of desire that comes
afterwards might be rooted in the original אונס. ones. Now that might
help explain your Patty Hearst case, right? So if you imagine a
case which is not... which is, you know, yes she's been held
captive all this time, I mean I think that's an interesting question,
right? About, right, how responsible do you see her for her later
actions if it resulted from this captivity. So that's what רבא's Rava
saying, that even if the person is willing and expresses complete willingness,
we all see this rooted in that original אונס. ones. Although again
רבא's Rava case is that it's all one act. I'm not sure
what he would say about a long-term thing, you know, over long-term
process. Alright, so what you have here is really fascinating issues of
defining אונס ones and רצון ratzon and you know, it starts as
I said pretty horrifically by imagining that this woman who's being raped
in the middle might... certainly אבוה דשמואל Avua de-Shmuel who says even
with her just being quiet and not protesting we're going to see
that not as just not trying to make, you know, normally you
would say, you know, why is she not protesting anymore? Because it's
not doing any good and it's just making things more difficult for
her and it doesn't mean at all that she wanted it or
whatever. So the first... The first hard point is that אבוה דשמואל
Avua d'Shmuel is going to interpret her silence as if she wants
it. Right? That's very hard to even begin to imagine and then
he says and therefore it's a problem, it's רצון. ratzon. And רבא
Rava goes to the opposite extreme. He doesn't maybe in that case
or שמואל Shmuel maybe he would say he wouldn't interpret the facts
the way אבוה דשמואל Avua d'Shmuel did. But even if it's explicit
and she says I want to be having sex with this guy,
we don't believe, you know, we believe that that all resulted from,
was was initiated by the original אונס onus and therefore cannot be
really defined as רצון. ratzon. So that's רבא's Rava position.
Okay. תניא כוותיה דרבא. Tanya kevasei deRava. We taught like רבא. Rava.
והיא לא נתפשה אסורה. Vehi lo nitpasa asura. It says again if
she was not taken, if she was not seized, she's forbidden to
her husband if she slept with another man. הנתפשה מותרת, Hanitpasa muteres,
if she was raped then she's permitted to go back to her
husband. ויש לך אחרת שאף על פי שלא נתפשה מותרת Ve'yesh acheres
she'af al pi shelo nitpasa muteres and there's another woman
even if she was not raped she's permissible to her husband. ואיזו
היא? Ve'eizo zo? Which is this? ואיזו היא זו? Ve'eizo zo? כל
שתחילתה באונס וסופה
ברצון. Kol shetechilasa be'ones vesofa beratzon. If it began by a force
even if in the end it was willing, then we would say
that she can go back to her husband. And yeah, I think
it is an interesting question, what if it's even over a longer
period of time? Like this case of, you know, that David was
discussing. Maybe that also would be considered אונס. onus. תניא אידך. Tanya
idach. We taught another ברייתא. braita. והיא לא נתפשה אסורה. Vehi lo
nitpasa asura. הנתפשה מותרת. Hanitpasa muteres. She was not raped, she's forbidden.
If she was raped, she's permitted. ויש לך אחרת שאף על פי
שנתפשה אסורה Ve'yesh acheres she'af al pi shenitpasa asura and there's another
woman even though she was raped she's forbidden to go back to
her husband. Even though, excuse me, even though she was raped it's
forbidden to go back to her husband. ואיזו היא? Ve'eizo zo? What
is this? אשת כהן. Eshet Kohen. ואיזו היא זו אשת כהן, Ve'eizo
zo Eshet Kohen, this is the wife of a כהן Kohen that
even a wife of a כהן Kohen who is raped is forbidden
to go back to her husband. That's the second part of the
ברייתא. Baraisa אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי ישמעאל. Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Yishmael. והיא לא נתפשה אסורה. Vehi lo
nitpasa asura. If she was not raped, she's forbidden. הנתפשה מותרת, Hanitpasa
muteres, if she was raped, she's permitted. ויש לך אחרת שאף על
פי שלא נתפשה מותרת Ve'yesh acheres she'af al pi shelo nitpasa muteres
and there's another woman that even though she was not raped and
even if she committed adultery she's permitted to go back to her
husband. What would be this woman? ואיזו היא? Ve'eizo zo? שקידושיה קידושי
טעות. Shekiddusheha kiddushei taut. This is that the original marriage was a
טעות. taut. שאפילו בנה מורכב על כתפה, She'afilu binah murkav al kteifeha,
even if her child is on her כתפה, kteifa, even if her
child is on her shoulder, ממאנת והולכת לה. mema'enes veholechet lah.
She can refuse, you know, her original husband and go free. Which
means basically, it's a woman married a guy, and she's been living
with him for ten years, and somehow you discover ten years later
that the whole thing was a טעות. taut I don't know what
a טעות was. She thought, you know, he had lied to her
about some essential thing. I mean, whatever, this happens actually. You want
a contemporary example of it? It turns out that he was gay.
Okay? And that he knew he was gay at the time that
they got married and he was hiding the fact and so on.
So, you know, I mean, whatever,
it's a disgusting contemporary פוסקים, poskim, but logically of course that should
be, you know, it should be, it should of course be defined
as a קידושי טעות. kiddushei taut. He wouldn't, shouldn't logically you shouldn't
even need a גט. get. Of course it was a mistake. Had
you known those facts that were being hidden from the person, then
they never would have gotten married. But they were married for ten
years and they had a kid or whatever. And then in the
course of it, she went ahead and she committed adultery. Okay? So
the הלכה halacha is she's not forbidden, like she didn't commit adultery,
I mean she wouldn't be forbidden to her husband if she wanted
to have sex with him again. She wouldn't be forbidden to the
man she had sex with because in the end it was a
קידושי טעות. kiddushei taut. And even if there's a child, it's still
the original wedding could be null and void even if they've been
living together for ten years and even if there are kids. Okay,
so there is a scenario where a woman can commit adultery and
not be forbidden if it turned out that the original marriage was
קידושי טעות. kiddushei taut. Okay. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. הני
נשי דגנבו גנבי שריין לגברייהו. Hanni nashei de'ganvu ganvei sharyan legavrayhu.
Women that are stolen by, taken captive by just like bandits can
go back to their husbands. Because if they were raped, it was
they wouldn't have done it willingly and therefore they can go back
to their husbands. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב יהודה, Amru lei Rabbanan leRav
Yehuda, so the rabbis said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, והא קא
ממטן להו נהמא? veha ka mamtan lehu nahama? What do you mean?
They seem like willing participants after they've been held, like, you know,
in the with Robin Hood and his merry men there in the
woods for a long time, they start participating, they bring them bread
for their meals. So, מחמת יראה, machmat yira, that's just because they're
afraid that if they don't participate, what's going to happen to them?
והא קא משלחן להו גירי? veha ka mishalchin lehu girei? But they
sort of hand them their arrows during when they're fighting in war,
you know, everything it seems like they're very willing participants. No, מחמת
יראה, machmat yira, that's all out of fear. Okay. ודאי שבקינהו ואזלו
מנפשייהו אסירן. Vadai shavkinnu ve'azlu minafshayhu assurun. If
there's no question that if the captors would say you're free to
go and they chose to stay, then they would be considered willing.
But otherwise, right, they are considered, you know, otherwise they're considered to
be doing it out of יראה. yira. You know, it's very interesting.
It plays out like the רמב"ם Rambam discusses in his אגרת השמד
Iggeret HaShmad about people that were under the threat of, like, you
know, that they had to convert out of, you know, to Islam
because or else, you know, risk being, you know, executed or whatever
and the רמב"ם Rambam talks about
like you know... that that
it's one thing to be sort of not observing while you're living
in those lands and you're afraid about what might happen to you
if you were to if you were to publicly, you know, observe
your Judaism. But he says, but that's as long as you don't
have an opportunity to leave, that you could be considered אונס onus
while you're there. As soon as you have an opportunity to leave
and you're not leaving, then he says then you can't be considered
an אונס onus anymore. So you know it's an interesting parallel to
this thing, like there's one thing to be seemingly doing things willingly,
like what does it mean to be forced? You don't always have
to have a gun to your head, like if you're not doing
this, you know, you're doing it because of your sense of the
overall threat and the consequences of what it would mean to do
otherwise. Okay, but once you actually have an opportunity to leave, that's
different. So this is very relevant to this issue, right, so there's
really like a range of scenarios about אונס, onus, right? There's the
אונס onus about literally, you know, physically at that moment being forced
and raped and so on. There's being in a context in which,
you know, you might act willingly, you know, you might willingly have
sex with the guy or, you know, do all these various things,
but it's because if you're not going to do that, you're afraid
what that the consequences, you're afraid for your life. And that actually
is also considered אונס. onus. Okay, so that all makes a lot
of sense. The question then is, when does it begin to become
רצון? ratzon? And there also we have two different like types of
scenarios. We have the case about like, you know, being raped and
in the middle of the act sort of saying, "Oh no, I
want it," where where at least we'll put aside אביי ושמואל, Abaye
u'Shmuel, at least, you know, at least רבא Rava says that that
case is not considered real רצון, ratzon, right? Because it's a resulting
from even if you're sincere, even if the woman is sincere, maybe
it's resulting from, you know, somehow the initial, again it's hard for
us to imagine how that initial act could lead to רצון, ratzon,
but anyway, but we'll frame it that way. And then I think
the more interesting question is the one that David raised, which isn't
directly addressed here, which is sort of the mirror image of this
case of אונס, onus, which is is that if a person maybe,
you know, or not a mirror, anyway, a person is given an
opportunity, maybe it is this case, a person is given an opportunity
to leave and they wind up staying, but maybe nevertheless it's all
ultimately can be seen as how they've been influenced and resulting from
the original thing. This last case seems to say against that, this
last case seems to say once they're given the opportunity to leave
and they don't leave, we can no longer frame it as אונס.
onus. Okay, but so so now the גמרא Gemara continues, wraps this
up. The גמרא Gemara's says like this. תנו
רבנן שבויי מלכות הרי הן כשבויין.
Tanu Rabbanan
shvuyei malchus harei hein keshvuyin. So ones that are taken captive by
the king are considered like captives and presumably for having sex with,
it literally means by like the government, but as we'll see in
a minute the גמרא's Gemara going to sound like it means by
the king for the purpose of having sex with the king, then
that's considered to be to be captives and it's אונס onus and
the women can go back to their to their to their husbands.
גנובי ליסטים אינם כשבויין. gnuvei listim einam keshvuyin. But once taken
by captors are not like שבויין shvuyin and they cannot go back
to their husbands. So the גמרא Gemara says והתניא איפכא, vehatanya ipcha,
don't we don't we but we have a ברייתא Baraisa that says
the exact
opposite? גמרא Gemara says מלכות אמלכות לא קשיא. malchus a'malchus lo kashya.
No, it's not difficult. הא במלכות אחשורוש הא במלכות בן נצר. ha
be'malchus Achashverosh ha be'malchus Ben Netzer. So if it's the king is
אחשורוש, Achashverosh, then רש"י Rashi says you know that unless you're אסתר,
Esther, the king is never going to marry you, never going to
take you for a wife. So therefore you're never really a willing
participant, okay, and therefore you're always it's always considered rape. If however
the guy is this guy בן נצר Ben Netzer who was apparently
some bandit but also he was a bandit that was actually seizing
a lot of territory and sort of starting up his own little
government, okay, he was like the I guess the ISIS of the
past or something like that. Anyway, and there you think that it
maybe if a woman is seized for sex by the by the
leader that maybe she'll be willing because maybe she wants to be
queen because you don't need to be of royal blood because this
guy's a commoner. Okay, so
that's that's why one says מלכות malchus is a problem and one
says it isn't. ליסטים אליסטים לא קשיא listim a'listim lo kashya and
the contradiction of the cases of bandits is not difficult. הא בבן
נצר, ha be'Ben Netzer, the other ברייתא Baraisa considers ליסטים listim to
be referring because בן נצר Ben Netzer was both a bandit and
a king as it were, he's a bandit king. So there you
go, so there so when it says that it that it is
a that a taken by a bandit we're we consider the woman
to have been willing, that was the case of בן נצר Ben
Netzer because maybe she wanted to do it because she wanted to
be queen. הא בליסטים דעלמא, ha be'listim de'alma, normal bandits, we assume
that she's not willing because why should she be willing and we'll
assume it's rape. ובן נצר, u'Ben Netzer, so how do you deal
with בן נצר? Ben Netzer? התם קרי ליה מלכא הכא קרי ליה
ליסטים, hatam kari lei malka hacha kari lei listim, in one ברייתא
Baraisa he's called a king and another ברייתא he's called a bandit?
אין דגבי אחשורוש ליסטים הוא, in de'gabbei Achashverosh listim hu, compared to
אחשורוש Achashverosh who's really of royal blood, he's a bandit. הוא וגבי
ליסטים דעלמא מלכא הוי, hu ve'gabbei listim de'alma malka havei, but by
other bandits he's a king. So there you go, it's like that
old joke, you know, the joke about the guy makes a million
dollars and he buys himself a yacht and he gets, you know,
he dresses up in his like sailor suit with the, you know,
brass buttons or whatever and he goes and shows has his little
sailor hat and he shows his mom he gives her like a
tour of the
yacht.
So all right anyway moving on
so what we have here is really like I said a very
on the one hand deeply disturbing גמרא Gemara in terms of thinking
that this woman in the middle of an act of rape can
be willingly participating but at the other hand an interesting גמרא Gemara
in terms of framing what's considered אונס onus and at the end
of the day the גמרא Gemara is let's just appreciate that at
the end of the day the גמרא Gemara is pretty broad in
defining אונס onus right אונס onus is even if in the middle
of the act she says no actually I want it and we
even if we think she's being sincere about saying she wants it
if you could imagine such a case we still say it resulted
from the original אונס onus and even if you know it's just
they're being held captive over a long period of time and they
seem to be willing nevertheless we say it's אונס onus because of
the fear of the you know because of the fear of what
will happen if they're not if they don't act in a willing
way but and the only way we won't consider it אונס onus
is if they're given an option to leave and then they don't
leave okay so that's in terms of אשת ישראל eshet yisrael now
we get to the כהנת kohenet okay and the גמרא Gemara here
is not focusing on the general issue which is also of course
you know just challenging about the way that חז"ל chazal understand that
the category in the תורה Torah of a זונה zonah is not
a woman who literally is a prostitute but any woman who's had
sex with a man that she's not able to marry and therefore
and whether it's willing or unwilling the idea that we understand that
the category of זונה zonah applies even in the case of unwilling
sex and that that makes this woman who is raped forbidden to
her husband that's the כהן kohen so the גמרא Gemara brackets that
I mean that's taken for granted and now we take a look
at the כתובה kesuvah aspects of
this okay ובכהנת אותבינך למדינתך u'bekohenet asvinach leadinatech and for a כהנת
kohenet he says I will return you to your country but I'm
not returning you as a wife because I won't be able to
stay married to you אמר אביי amar abbaye אלמנה לכהן גדול חייב
לפדותה almanah lekohen gadol chayav liftotah let's say a כהן גדול kohen
gadol married an אלמנה almanah okay or you could say a כהן
kohen married a גרושה grusha anyway he has to redeem her שאני
קורא בה she'ani korei bah because I read because the line in
the כתובה kesuvah applies to her ובכהנת אהדרינך למדינתך u'bekohenet adrinach leadinatech
he says I will return you to your country so therefore he
still has those obligations because those obligations apply even if she is
not allowed to remain his wife so even this woman who began
as not his
wife—excuse me—she began as his wife but it was not legally not
allowed to be her husband nevertheless those obligations still obtain now what
I have to explain is the following surprisingly right I think you
all remember from whatever things we've done in the past that
קידושין kiddushin באיסורי לאוין b'issurei la'avim is binding if a כהן kohen
marries a גרושה grusha כהן גדול kohen gadol marries an אלמנה almanah
ישראל yisrael marries a ממזרת mamzeret the קידושין kiddushin is still binding
they're married and you need a גט get and if the woman
were to commit adultery it would be adultery not only that what
you might be really surprised to find out is that the כתובה
kesuvah obligations even exist now you might have said why are the
rabbis imposing the כתובה kesuvah obligations you know if they basically would
want this couple to get divorced so the only—the כתובה kesuvah obligations
which exist are the ones which are not about their ongoing marital
status so for example the lump sum payment she gets at divorce
that exists because right why should she you know I mean why
should she be out her I mean you know the money to
protect her whatever you know and she still needs that's you know
of course you could argue the opposite you could argue that that
money is in order that he shouldn't casually divorce her right that
was one of the reasons for for that lump sum payment but
nevertheless it's a payment that's made not as part of their ongoing
marriage it's a payment that's made once they're divorced so she still
gets that okay however she does not get for example
food right
and רפואה refuah and all those types of things are the types
of ongoing financial obligations that is part of them remaining married and
we want to encourage them to get divorced so we want to
basically say you don't get any of those ongoing payments and therefore
it's not in your financial interest to remain married right and therefore
that hopefully will encourage will encourage divorce of course funny thing is
that makes it easier for the husband he doesn't have to pay
any money so in a way he's the one we gotta encourage
to get divorced not her anyway we don't want to maintain those
כתובה kesuvah obligations that are about their ongoing maintaining their ongoing marital
you know marriage okay
so what about the obligation to redeem her so that actually is
not about sustaining the ongoing marriage because for a כהן kohen the
obligation to redeem her is actually and then he's going to redeem
her and then they're going to get divorced right because by a
כהן kohen he can't remain married to her anyway so that's what
the statement here is that if basically it was a—an illicit marriage
but it was still binding אלמנה לכהן גדול almanah lekohen gadol and
it was about a כהן kohen then he does have the obligation
to redeem her because that's not an obligation that is in the
context of them remaining married however if you look at the next
line and it'll help clarify it top finally we get to today's
דף ממזרת ונתינה לישראל אינו חייב לפדותה mamzeret u'netinah l'yisrael eino chayav
liftotah if
however it was a ישראל yisrael who married a ממזרת. mamzeret. anything,
he does not have to redeem her. Why? כאין אני קורי בו
ואותבינך לי לאינתו Ke'ein ani kurei bo ve'oshvitech li le'intu because then
the line I will return you as my wife doesn't apply. So
I mean what the גמרא's Gemara explicitly said here is that whether
the line of the כתובה kesuvah applies in this case or not.
What I'm telling you and which is based on what רש״י Rashi
says, what רש״י Rashi clarifies is that it's also that we will
not, we will not
maintain the כתובה kesuvah obligations, we will not uphold the כתובה kesuvah.
obligations if they are in the context of them remaining married in
this type of a case where the marriage is forbidden.
Meaning if you're under the same roof at that point?
No, meaning if the nature of the obligation reflects the idea that
they're going to remain husband and wife.
Even if they're under the
same, even if they're under the same roof. So if the case
by the כהנת Kohenet and the what do you call it? the
אלמנה almanah to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or גרושה grushah to
a כהן, Kohen, since the after redeeming they're not supposed to remain
married, so we cannot the obligation to redeem still applies. Whereas by
a כהן Kohen and a ממזרת, mamzeret, since the nature obligation of
redeeming, the normal obligation of redeeming is and then you remain married,
so in this case where they're not supposed to remain married, the
obligation of redeeming does not apply.
מדינה Medinah here means country and not city?
Probably city, yeah, you're right. Okay, דאין אני קורא בו ואותבינך לי
לאינתו. De'ein ani korei bo ve'oshvitech li le'intu. רבא אמר Rava amar
כל שיסור שבויה גורם לה חייב לפדותה. kol she'issur shvuyah gorem lah
chayav lispotah. איסור דבר אחר גורם לה אינו חייב לפדותה. issur davar
acher gorem lah eino chayav lispotah. רבא Rava says no, when the
כתובה kesuvah says I'll redeem I'll return you to your country to
your city, meaning even though you won't remain my wife, that only
means that you won't remain my wife as a result of what
do you call it? as a result of the fact that you
were taken captive, meaning I still will have an obligation to redeem
you even though you were taken captive and even though as a
result of that I won't be able to keep you as my
wife. But if I'm not able to keep you as my wife
for another reason, like you're an אלמנה almanah or you were a
גרושה grushah etc., then in that case I I don't have any
obligation to redeem you. Okay, so the fact that the language of
the כתובה kesuvah suggests that the obligation to redeem applies even if
they can't remain husband and wife, רבא Rava says it's only if
they can't remain husband and wife as a result of her being
taken as a שבויה. shvuyah. But if there's another reason that they
shouldn't have been husband and wife to begin with because it was
an אלמנה almanah or was a גרושה grushah or whatever it might
have been, then then that obligation doesn't apply because that obligation is
fundamentally an obligation between husband and wife and they shouldn't have been
husband and wife to begin with. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says לימא
כתנאי. leima katanai.
Let's say that this is linked to a debate of תנאים tannaim
because we taught the following. המדיר את אשתו ונשבית. Hamadir es ishto
venishbeis. A person makes a vow that his wife can't get any
benefit from him. Now, if he takes the vow that his wife
can't get any benefit from him, he has to divorce his wife
because you can't live together as husband and wife with such a
vow. Okay, so this is basically just sets up a scenario where
he is obligated to divorce her. So they're already in a scenario
where they're obligated to get divorced and then she gets taken captive.
רבי אליעזר אומר פודה ונותן לה כתובתה. Rabbi Eliezer omer podeh venosein
lah kesuvatah. You have to redeem her because that's your כתובה Kesuvah
obligation and then you have to divorce her and give her the
כתובה Kesuvah because you guys gotta get divorced. רבי יהושע אומר נותן
לה כתובתה ואינו פודה. Rabbi Yehoshua omer nosein lah kesuvatah ve'eino podeh.
No, you pay out her כתובה Kesuvah because you gotta get divorced,
but you don't have to redeem her.
אמר רבי נתן שאלתי את סומכוס, Amar Rabbi Nassan sha'alti es Sumchus,
who is a student of
רבי מאיר, כשאמר רבי יהושע kshe'amar Rabbi Yehoshua נותן לה כתובתה ואינו
פודה, nosein lah kesuvatah ve'eino podeh, that you can just pay out
her כתובה and you don't have to redeem her, right you divorce
her but you don't redeem. כשהדירה ולבסוף נשבית, keshehdirah ulevasof nishbeis, would
this be only if the vow preceded her being taken captive? Because
then they were already in a state where they had to get
divorced when she was taken captive. או נשבית ולבסוף הדירה, o nishbeis
ulevasof hdirah, would it be even if she was first taken captive
and then he made a vow? ואמר לי ve'amar li and he
said to me לא שמעתי, lo shamati, you know what, I didn't
hear explicitly, ונראין הדברים venirin hadavarim but it seems כשהדירה ולבסוף נשבית,
keshehdirah ulevasof nishbeis, that it would only he would only have an
obligation if first she took a vow and they were obligated to
get divorced and then she was taken captive. So when she was
taken captive they were already you know getting divorced as it were.
So therefore his obligation to redeem her didn't apply.
דאי אמרת, de'i amarta, because now the גמרא Gemara adds in you
can tell by the shift to Aramaic, because were you to say
נשבית ולבסוף הדירה, nishbeis ulevasof hdirah, that if she was taken captive
and then he took a vow and then he would have to
redeem her because then אתי לאירומי, ati l'irumai, he's going to you
know scheme. Right, here's a great way of getting out of how
to redeem your wife. She's taken captive, it's they're asking $100,000, that's
a כתובה obligation, but the actual כתובה itself, the lump sum payment
of the כתובה is 10,000. So why don't I do this? Why
don't I take a vow? Now we're obligated to get divorced and
now I don't have to redeem her and now I'll just pay
out her כתובה. So obviously it would only be that the vow
preceded. Okay, but what do you see from this? You see that
there's a debate, a case of a husband and wife that have
to get divorced, is there a כתובה obligation or not a כתובה
obligation? Right, that's the question, I mean is there a an obligation
to redeem or not an obligation to redeem when a husband and
wife have to get divorced. So maybe this parallels this whole discussion.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו. mai lav. Are we not
talking about דמדיר אשתו כי מפלגי? de-madir ishto ki mifligi?
That we're talking about the only reason that you might have an
obligation since you're- how could you- since you have to get divorced
is that it's the wife of a כהן. Kohen. אביי דאמר כרבי
אליעזר Abaye d'amar k'Rabbi Eliezer ורבא דאמר כרבי יהושע. ve-Rava d'amar k'Rabbi
Yehoshua. And אביי Abaye is like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבא
Rava is like רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, which means the following. And
we'll end with this now. But if we're talking about not the
wife of a כהן, Kohen, the גמרא at this stage imagines that
of course you would not have to redeem her, because the כתובה
by a non-wife of a כהן Kohen says, I'll redeem you to
me as a wife, I'll bring you back to me as a
wife. And since they were- when she was taken captive, they were
in the process of getting divorced and they had to get divorced,
it's not possible to say I'll bring you back as a wife.
So it assumes that if it was the wife of a כהן,
Kohen, nobody would say it. This case would be as the wife
of a ישראל. Yisrael. This case is a wife of a כהן.
Kohen. And therefore it's a wife of a כהן, Kohen, so even
though they had to get divorced, the כתובה still says, I'll redeem
you even though we won't stay married, I'll redeem you and bring
you back to your city. And that seems to be the debate.
In a case where some other thing other than her captivity is
preventing them from staying married, by the case of a wife of
a כהן, Kohen, are you still- is he going to still be
obligated to redeem her or not? The language of the כתובה says-
does- says
I'll bring you back, not that you'll be my wife, so maybe
the obligation would still exist. Or maybe it would say since before
the captivity they were obligated to get divorced, then fundamentally the obligation
to redeem does not exist. Okay, so we'll continue with this tomorrow.
All right, I have no idea how we are going to catch
up. And...
Oh, that is true, it's a longer שבת. Shabbos.
Yeah, it's שבת הגדול, Shabbos HaGadol, we can do it after מנחה.
Mincha. Are we going to have the...